<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-04-18T11:57:55+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">My awesome title</title><subtitle>Write an awesome description for your new site here. You can edit this line in _config.yml. It will appear in your document head meta (for Google search results) and in your feed.xml site description.</subtitle><author><name>vinay hegde</name></author><entry><title type="html">Running Cassandra and PostgreSQL in Docker</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/07/27/Running-Cassandra-and-Postgres-in-Docker.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Running Cassandra and PostgreSQL in Docker" /><published>2020-07-27T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-07-27T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/07/27/Running-Cassandra-and-Postgres-in-Docker</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/07/27/Running-Cassandra-and-Postgres-in-Docker.html">&lt;p&gt;Today I started thee Udacity &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.udacity.com/course/data-engineer-nanodegree--nd027&quot;&gt;Data Engineering Nanodegree&lt;/a&gt; and wanted to follow along the demo projects in Lesson 1 on my local machine. (However, this is optional as Udacity provides the environment in their workspace).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post I describe how to set up the environment using Docker containers for Cassandra and Postgres so that you don’t have to install them locally, which is rather cumbersome, especially for Cassandra as you need to install Java first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-creating-cassandra-and-postgres-docker-containers-with-docker-compose&quot;&gt;1. Creating Cassandra and Postgres Docker containers with docker-compose&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Create &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;docker-compose.yml&lt;/code&gt; (with exactly this name) with the following content:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-docker highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;version: &apos;2&apos;

networks:
  app-tier:
    driver: bridge

services:
  cassandra:
    image: &apos;cassandra:latest&apos;
    networks:
      - app-tier
    expose: 
      - &apos;6000&apos;
    ports:
      - &apos;6000:9042&apos;
  postgres:
    image: &apos;postgres:latest&apos;
    restart: always
    environment:
      POSTGRES_PASSWORD: example
    expose:
      - &apos;7000&apos;
    ports:
      - &apos;7000:5432&apos;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here I connect container ports 9042 (for Cassandra) and 5432 (for Postgres), which are default used by these services, with the host ports, here specified as 6000 and 7000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Creating a yml-document ensures that you don’t have to set up containers each time you want to use them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To run Docker containers, you just need to type &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;docker-compose up&lt;/code&gt; in your terminal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Optional&lt;/strong&gt;: if you want to check whether Cassandra runs properly, you need first to attach shell to &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;cassandra:latest&lt;/code&gt; container (I will not go into details here, I do it in Visual Studio Code where I have installed Docker extension - more on it &lt;a href=&quot;https://code.visualstudio.com/docs/containers/overview&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;) and type &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;cqlsh&lt;/code&gt; to run a command line shell for interacting with Cassandra through CQL (the Cassandra Query Language). If no errors thrown, congratulations - you can now use Cassandra docker and run CQL queries. Type &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;exit&lt;/code&gt; to exit the cqlsh terminal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a similar way, you can check whether PostgreSQL runs properly - attach shell to &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;postgres:latest&lt;/code&gt; and type &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;psql --username=postgres&lt;/code&gt; to log in as created by default postgres user. Now you can type &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;\l&lt;/code&gt; to see the existing databases, one of which is &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;postgres&lt;/code&gt; which we will be connecting to in Jupyter Notebooks. Type &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;exit&lt;/code&gt; to exit the psql terminal. Type &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;exit&lt;/code&gt; again if you want to exit container shell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, if you wish to stop the container, just press &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Ctrl+C&lt;/code&gt; in your terminal. Or check which docker containers are running with &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;docker ps&lt;/code&gt; command in your terminal and then type &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;docker kill &amp;lt;container-ID as listed when running docker ps command&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;, replacing the phrase in &amp;lt;&amp;gt; with corresponding ID.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-setting-up-environment-for-data-engineering-nanodegree&quot;&gt;2. Setting up environment for Data Engineering Nanodegree&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the rest of this post, I describe how to create a virtual environment for Data Engineering Nanodegree and run the jupyter notebooks provided in Lesson 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;21-create-new-pyenv-environment&quot;&gt;2.1. Create new pyenv environment&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In your terminal, go to a folder where you’re going to save all data for Data Engineering Nanodegree and create a new virtual envirnment by running:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pyenv virtualenv &amp;lt;python version&amp;gt; &amp;lt;name of virtual environment&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;, replacing &amp;lt;&amp;gt; with your own values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, I created a new virtual environment called “dataengineer” using my current Python version 3.8.2 like so:
&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pyenv virtualenv 3.8.2 dataengineer&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To check which Python version is installed on your computer, try &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pyenv version&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then we activate the new virtual environment with &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pyenv activate dataengineer&lt;/code&gt; and install the following packages:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pip install jupyter notebook&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pip install psycopg2-binary&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pip install cassandra-driver&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that I installed the binary version of psycopg2, as I have an error thrown if I try installing psycopg2 as suggested by Udacity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;22-connect-to-cassandra-and-postgresql-database-in-jupyter-notebook&quot;&gt;2.2. Connect to Cassandra and PostgreSQL database in Jupyter Notebook&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After completing steps 1 and 2.1., you can now start using Cassandra within Jupyter Notebook “L1_Demo_2_Creating_a_Table_with_Apache_Cassandra” by specifying the host port from container as following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-python highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;cassandra.cluster&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Cluster&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;try&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; 
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;cluster&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Cluster&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;([&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&apos;127.0.0.1&apos;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;],&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;port&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;6000&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;#If you have a locally installed Apache Cassandra instance
&lt;/span&gt;    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;session&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;cluster&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;connect&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;except&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;Exception&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;e&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;e&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the same way, you can start PostgreSQL within Jupyter Notebook “L1_Demo_0_creating-a-table-with-postgres” by specifying the host port and password from container as following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-python highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;conn&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;psycopg2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;connect&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;host=127.0.0.1 port=7000 dbname=postgres user=postgres password=example&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use this connection and cluster for all other jupyter notebooks in Lesson 1.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>vinay hegde</name></author><category term="Udacity Nanodegree" /><category term="Data Engineering" /><category term="Docker" /><category term="Cassandra" /><category term="PostgreSQL" /><summary type="html">How to set up the environment for Udacity Data Engineering Nanodegree on your local machine</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Udacity Review: Digital Marketing Nanodegree</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/06/04/Udacity-Review-Digital-Marketing-Nanodegree.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Udacity Review: Digital Marketing Nanodegree" /><published>2020-06-04T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-06-04T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/06/04/Udacity%20Review:%20Digital%20Marketing%20Nanodegree</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/06/04/Udacity-Review-Digital-Marketing-Nanodegree.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/udacity-digital-marketing-nanodegree.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Udacity Digital Marketing Nanodegree Certificate&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Udacity offered 1 month for free and I decided to enroll into &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.udacity.com/course/digital-marketing-nanodegree--nd018&quot;&gt;Digital Marketing Nanodegree&lt;/a&gt;, mainly for two reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, I am interested in Data Science for Marketing and Product Analytics, so I thought expanding my knowledge into Digital Marketing would help me better understand marketing problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, I had previous experience with Udacity Nanodegrees (see my review of &lt;a href=&quot;/Udacity-Data-Science-Nanodegree/&quot;&gt;Data Science program here&lt;/a&gt;) and decided to challenge myself to graduate within a free month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So given my motivation above, I will answer the following questions in this review:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is the Digital Marketing Nanodegree worth to pursue, especially when there are many free resources on the subject?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How long does it take to complete the program?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;digital-marketing-nanodegree-overview&quot;&gt;Digital Marketing Nanodegree: Overview&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tools&lt;/strong&gt;: Google Analytics, Google AdWords, Facebook Ad Manager, Google’s PageSpeed, SEMrush, MOZ, MailChimp&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The program is structured around core digital marketing sectors that provide good foundations into digital marketing landscape:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Content Marketing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Social Media Marketing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Social Media Advertising&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Search Engine Optimization&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Search Engine Marketing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Display Advertising&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Email Marketing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Google Analytics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the start you have to choose which marketing challenge you want to pursue:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;B2C: Digital Marketing Nanodegree (DMND) Program&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;B2B: Enterprise’s DMND Corporate Training&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;marketing for your own company&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once chosen, you will work through the program to create a marketing strategy for your “product”. This means that your projects will be around this marketing challenge. So if you chose B2C option, for instance, you will create a Target Persona, generate leads with Facebook campaign, create email workflow for DMND only.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are 10 projects to complete:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prepare to Market&lt;/strong&gt;: develop a target persona, formulate marketing objective and KPI&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Market your Content&lt;/strong&gt;: write a blog post and promote it via social posts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Run a Facebook Ad Campaign Part 1&lt;/strong&gt;: create a campaign and run it&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Run a Facebook Ad Campaign Part 2&lt;/strong&gt;: analyze results and provide recommendations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conduct a SEO Audit&lt;/strong&gt;: recommend a target keyword list and how to optimize for ranking in search engine results&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Run an AdWords Campaign Part 1&lt;/strong&gt;: create a campaign &amp;amp; run it&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Run an AdWords Campaign Part 2&lt;/strong&gt;: analyze results and provide recommendations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Evaluate a Display Campaign&lt;/strong&gt;: analyze results and provide recommendations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Market with Email&lt;/strong&gt;: develop email plan, create email with MailChimp and evaluate the results&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Create Digital Marketing Portfolio&lt;/strong&gt;: develop a marketing budget and get all other projects together in one place&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For both campaigns you actually run you get a budget - $100 for Facebook and ~$50 for Google AdWords. So you spend real money on advertising like on a job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;pros-360-degree-overview--hands-on-experience-in-running-campaigns&quot;&gt;Pros: 360-degree overview + hands-on experience in running campaigns&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DMND lives up to its promise - you learn 360-degree of Digital Marketing landscape, which I think not every program out there does. It is good introductory course for those who would like to decide which career path in digital marketing to take, and as it turned out there are plenty! From more creative jobs like content Strategist or Email Marketing Manager to more technical like SEO Analyst or Marketing Analyst.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I liked the most is that DMND provides &lt;strong&gt;a good overview over the job market&lt;/strong&gt; - job descriptions with common titles, average base salary, skills for the job and typical responsibilities from 8 different digital marketing sectors. They also recorded videos with professionals that explain what their day-to-day work looks like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And probably the most valuable skill that this program teaches you is &lt;strong&gt;running actual campaigns on Facebook and Google AdWords&lt;/strong&gt;. For this, you really need to have a business account. Unless you run a small business or already working in digital marketing, you won’t be able to get this experience. I also liked that I could see other students’ campaigns and learned a lot from analyzing their approaches and what works best. So you really benefit from getting an access to Udacity accounts on Facebook Ads Manager and Google AdWords. They also give you free access for 30 days to SEMrush, which has great tools for SEO and competitive research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I think Digital Marketing is a good starting point and has many advantages over other programs/courses out there. You learn by doing, not only reading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;cons-not-difficult-but-extensive&quot;&gt;Cons: not difficult but extensive&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would grade the program as not very difficult. However, it has &lt;strong&gt;10 different projects&lt;/strong&gt; that you need to complete in order to graduate. As a result, I underestimated time needed and did not finish in 1 month as planned (I also had some other projects I worked on alongside studying). Despite this, I decided to prolong the program for another month since I felt that I learned a lot (and was grateful for what I learned), accomplished a lot and did not want to lose that progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, &lt;strong&gt;1,5 months on 1.5x listening speed&lt;/strong&gt; is realistic estimate for those who took MOOCs before. I find DMND on monthly basis still expensive - $400. But there is a trick: if you unsubscribe and give program cost as a reason, they will try to win your back and give a discount.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Final advice to those who are more into &lt;strong&gt;Data Analytics/ Data Science&lt;/strong&gt; like me and consider taking Digital Marketing Nanodegree for the same reason as mine - don’t expect much. The program is not technical and doesn’t teach Marketing for Machine Learning tasks. That said, I do understand the key Marketing metrics better and how Marketing functions after completing the program. But you probably can learn this on a job as well. As I am in career transition and don’t have formal business education, I think completing a Digital Marketing Nanodegree is a nice add-on to my skills and knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>vinay hegde</name></author><category term="Udacity Nanodegree Review" /><category term="Digital Marketing" /><summary type="html">Is Digital Marketing Nanodegree by Udacity worth it?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Troubleshooting: XML Sitemap when hosting on GitHub</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/05/01/XML-Sitemap-Problem-when-hosting-on-GitHub.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Troubleshooting: XML Sitemap when hosting on GitHub" /><published>2020-05-01T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-05-01T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/05/01/XML-Sitemap-Problem-when-hosting-on-GitHub</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/05/01/XML-Sitemap-Problem-when-hosting-on-GitHub.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TLDR: Don’t commit your auto-generated sitemap.xml to GitHub. It won’t be updated&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-sitemap-is-important&quot;&gt;Why sitemap is important?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sitemaps encourage crawling. So if you want your site to be “discovered” by Google, it’s better to have an up-to-date sitemap. You can check your website’s indexing state in Google Search Console by going to the Coverage tab or simply by typing &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;site:yourwebsite.com&lt;/code&gt; in Google.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;notice--info text-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;far fa-sticky-note&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt;  For small site’s with fewer than 500 pages and well-linked structure, sitemap is not necessary - Google will index all pages anyway. Still, it’s better to monitor the indexing “health” of your site as it grows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;context&quot;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I host my Minimal Mistakes Jekyll site on GitHub Pages and commit all the changes there. 
sitemap.xml is autogenerated with &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll-sitemap/blob/master/Gemfile&quot;&gt;jekyll-sitemap plugin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;problem&quot;&gt;Problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unindexed pages as shown in Google Search Console&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Index Coverage report in Google Search Console gave me 1 error message and 12 pages that were indexed, but not submitted in sitemap:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/Sitemap-XML-Google-Search-Console-1000.png&quot; alt=&quot;Index Coverage Report in Google Search Console&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      Index Coverage Report in Google Search Console

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;solution&quot;&gt;Solution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Delete sitemap.xml from GitHub&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building site locally showed no sitemap problems, so jekyll-plugin worked as intended. 
The problem was that I committed the sitemap.xml to GitHub Pages where I host my site. When generating the site, GitHub also generates the new sitemap.xml via jekyll-plugin. But because such file already existed (the old version that was committed earlier), it simply ignored the new version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mistake is really stupid. Hope you learned from this post not to make it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>vinay hegde</name></author><category term="Google Search Console" /><category term="Minimal Mistakes Jekyll" /><category term="GitHub Pages" /><summary type="html">How to check Indexing state with Google Search Console</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to improve SEO by boosting website speed</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/04/27/How-to-improve-SEO-by-boosting-website-speed.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to improve SEO by boosting website speed" /><published>2020-04-27T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-04-27T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/04/27/How-to-improve-SEO-by-boosting-website-speed</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/04/27/How-to-improve-SEO-by-boosting-website-speed.html">&lt;p&gt;Recently I taught myself how to conduct technical audit to improve SEO and want to share my knowledge here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My two reasons for speed slowdown were &lt;strong&gt;Image Sizes&lt;/strong&gt; and  &lt;strong&gt;Font Awesome&lt;/strong&gt;. Read on to learn my solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;notice--info text-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;far fa-sticky-note&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; Although my solutions are universal, I have some specific advice for those who built their website with &lt;a href=&quot;https://mmistakes.github.io/minimal-mistakes/docs/quick-start-guide/&quot;&gt;Minimal Mistakes Jekyll theme&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/Personal-website-with-Minimal-Mistakes-Jekyll-Theme-HOWTO-Part-III/&quot;&gt;run it on GitHub Pages&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-speed-matters&quot;&gt;Why speed matters?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Website’s speed affects a lot of important metrics such as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the ranking position in Google Search results&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;bounce rate&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;conversion rate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just by reducing the page load time from 3 seconds to 1 second, you can reduce bounce rate by 32%, according to &lt;a href=&quot;https://support.google.com/webmasters/answer/9205520&quot;&gt;Google data&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google also created a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thinkwithgoogle.com/feature/testmysite/&quot;&gt;useful tool&lt;/a&gt; that allows you to measure the impact of a faster site on your revenue. Here’s an example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/Google-Lighthouse-speed-revenue-impact-tool.png&quot; alt=&quot;Google tool to evaluate impact of a website speed on revenue&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;running-speed-test&quot;&gt;Running Speed Test&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can run speed test in two (identical) ways:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;with Page Speed Insights from Google Search Console Speed tab&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/Google-Lighthouse-PageSpeed-Insights-1500.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;PageSpeed Insights in Google Search Console&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;From Chrome Dev Tools Audits tab (Lighthouse)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/Google-Lighthouse-audit-tab-1000.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Google Lighthouse Audit tab&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both tests produce reports across mobile and desktop devices. While Google’s PageSpeed Insight tool shows you only the Performance score, Lighthouse tool accessible from Chrome Dev Tools provides few more metrics on top of Performance such as Accessibility, Best Practices and SEO.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;notice--info text-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;far fa-sticky-note&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; If you want to learn more about Lighthouse Score components and how they are created, checkout this official &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1up5rxd4EMCoMaxH8cppcK1x76n6HLx0e7jxb0e0FXvc/edit#gid=283330180&quot;&gt;Lighthouse Score Weighting doc&lt;/a&gt;. There is also a free &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.udacity.com/course/website-performance-optimization--ud884&quot;&gt;Website Performance Optimization course&lt;/a&gt; on Udacity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;benchmark-score&quot;&gt;Benchmark Score&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tools such as Lighthouse or PageSpeed Insights allow you to test the speed of any page of your website. I decided to start with the main page - https://www.cross-validated.com&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I first checked my blog’s performance, it turned out that the page speed was really good for desktop version (98/100) but only average for mobile version (56/100 rating):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/Google-Lighthouse-PageSpeed-Insights-results-1500.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Google PageSpeed Insight results for cross-validated mobile&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      Page Speed Rating on Mobile before Optimization

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Troubleshooting why it took so long for my website to load, I came down to two main delay sources - &lt;strong&gt;Large Images&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Font Awesome&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;speed-delay-sources&quot;&gt;Speed Delay Sources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;large-images&quot;&gt;Large Images&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Large image sizes are really critical for the site’s mobile version. It turned out that my avatar was 1.3 Mb and it was one main reason for the average audit score. Interestingly, this wasn’t a problem for the desktop version, where I got a score of almost 100.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I knew that big image sizes adversly affect the load time. But how big is big? Before I thought that the image quality is the king and the size around 400 kb is really small. Now I try to optimize my images and resize them to get good quality with the maximum image size around 100 Kb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I batch resize image files from Mac Terminal using native &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;sips&lt;/code&gt; (scriptable image processing system) like so&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:ft1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:ft1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-terminal highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;gp&quot;&gt;#&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;Batch Resize 
&lt;span class=&quot;go&quot;&gt;sips -Z 800 *.png

&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;gp&quot;&gt;#&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;Batch Convert PNG to JPG
&lt;span class=&quot;gp&quot;&gt;mkdir jpegs;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;sips &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;-s&lt;/span&gt; format jpeg &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;--out&lt;/span&gt; jpegs
&lt;span class=&quot;go&quot;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;gp&quot;&gt;#&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;Batch Convert JPG to PNG
&lt;span class=&quot;gp&quot;&gt;mkdir pngs;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;sips &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;-s&lt;/span&gt; format png &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;--out&lt;/span&gt; pngs
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For screen shots captured automatically with &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Command+Shift+4&lt;/code&gt; on Mac, it works best if you first resize the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;png&lt;/code&gt; screen shot and then convert it to &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;jpeg&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;notice--info text-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;far fa-sticky-note&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; There is a nice Jekyll plugin to automatically resize images - &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rbuchberger/jekyll_picture_tag&quot;&gt;Picture Tag&lt;/a&gt;. However, if you host your website on GitHub Pages like me, you can’t use this tool because it is not supported by GitHub Pages. &lt;a href=&quot;https://help.github.com/en/github/working-with-github-pages/about-github-pages-and-jekyll&quot;&gt;GitHub Pages cannot build sites using unsupported plugins&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; 
 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;font-awesome&quot;&gt;Font Awesome&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Font Awesome provides Twitter, LinkedIN, GitHub and other icons on my blog. Before optimization, it was delivered as JavaScript and was very slow to load.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solution is to load a &lt;strong&gt;CSS version of Font Awesome instead of JavaScript&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are using &lt;strong&gt;Jekyll Minimal Mistakes theme&lt;/strong&gt; like me, you can switch to Font Awesome CSS like so:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Go to &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;head.html&lt;/code&gt; and add Font-Awesome minified CSS delivered from Cloudflare CDN as a second line after &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;main.css&lt;/code&gt; like so:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-md highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;!-- For all browsers --&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;link&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;rel=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;stylesheet&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;href=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;/assets/css/main.css&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;link&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;rel=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;stylesheet&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;href=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/font-awesome/5.9.0/css/all.min.css&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Delete the referral to Font Awesome JavaScript from &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_includes/scripts.html&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-md highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;script &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;src=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;https://kit.fontawesome.com/4eee35f757.js&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;performance-score-after-optimization&quot;&gt;Performance Score after Optimization&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Resizing large images and switching to CSS for Font Awesome boosted the page’s performance score from 59 to 97 on mobile:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/Google-Lighthouse-after-Optimization-1500.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Google PageSpeed Insight results for cross-validated mobile after optimization&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      Page Speed Rating on Mobile after Optimization

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;further-testing-and-unresolved-problems&quot;&gt;Further Testing and Unresolved Problems&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Testing pages with posts, however, showed again average results (around 80/100). The major problem is that I’m using several third-party JavaScript providers such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Disqus (commenting platform)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Google Analytics&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Google Tag Manager (Google Optimize was installed with GTM)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;MathJax&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Switching off Disqus, for instance, almost halved Time to Interactive (from 11s to 6s). Right now, I am not ready to give up on Disqus. So I think this is a trade-off I have to face.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another problem that I can’t solve right now is the caching time of static assets. Since I’m hosting on GitHub Pages, I cannot change cache policy which apparently is only 10 m for images on GitHub. :( Now thinking about about moving my site to AWS cloud.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:ft1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Learned about it thanks to &lt;a href=&quot;http://tutorialshares.com/batch-convert-png-jpg-mac-terminal/&quot;&gt;Tutorial Shares&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:ft1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>vinay hegde</name></author><category term="Google Lighthouse" /><category term="Minimal Mistakes Jekyll" /><category term="SEO" /><category term="PageSpeed Insights" /><summary type="html">How to Run Website Speed Test with Google PageSpeed Insights</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to Correctly Set Up Internal IP Filter in Google Analytics</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/04/21/How-to-Correctly-Set-Up-Internal-IP-Filter-in-Google-Analytics.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to Correctly Set Up Internal IP Filter in Google Analytics" /><published>2020-04-21T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-04-21T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/04/21/How-to-Correctly-Set-Up-Internal-IP-Filter-in-Google-Analytics</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/04/21/How-to-Correctly-Set-Up-Internal-IP-Filter-in-Google-Analytics.html">&lt;p&gt;Google Analytics allows you to filter out data based on IPs, which comes handy when you want to exclude your own views.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that my internal IP filter did not work properly and my Google Analytics data all this time was contaminated by my own page views. :(&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to avoid my mistakes, read through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;notice--info text-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;far fa-sticky-note&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; It is important to note from the start that applying Filter in Google Analytics is permanent, meaning that Google Analytics will not record excluded data and you will not be able to access it at later stage. So use Filters precautiously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;setting-up-internal-ip-filter-in-google-analytics&quot;&gt;Setting up Internal IP Filter in Google Analytics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Go to Admin and choose &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;All Filters&lt;/code&gt; from left pane:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/Google-Analytics-Product-Linking.png&quot; alt=&quot;Google Analytics Admin page&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Click &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Add Filter&lt;/code&gt; and configure it like so, inserting your IP adress respectively:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/Google-Analytics-Internal-Filter.png&quot; alt=&quot;Google Analytics Filter Page&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;notice--info text-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;far fa-sticky-note&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; If you don’t know your IP address, just google “What is my IP address”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have here two views - &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;All Web Site Data&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Test View&lt;/code&gt;. This will be useful later when we will be testing the internal Filter. So if you don’t have the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Test View&lt;/code&gt; create it now (Admin -&amp;gt; Create View on the right pane).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make sure that you added only &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;All Web Site Data&lt;/code&gt; to Selected views, while &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Test View&lt;/code&gt; is not selected. Don’t forget to Save.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;troubleshooting-1---no-ip-anonymization&quot;&gt;Troubleshooting 1 - No IP Anonymization&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Theoretically, setting up the Filter as described above should suffice. My mistake, however, was to allow IP anonymization on my Minimal Mistakes website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So you want to make sure that &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;anonymize_ip&lt;/code&gt; is set to false in &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_config.yml&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-yml highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# Analytics&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;analytics&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;provider               &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;google-gtag&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# false (default), &quot;google&quot;, &quot;google-universal&quot;, &quot;custom&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;google&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;tracking_id          &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;UA-XXXXXXXXX-1&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;anonymize_ip         &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;no&quot;&gt;false&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# false (default)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;optimize_id          &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;GTM-XXXXXXX&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;troubleshooting-2---checking-filter&quot;&gt;Troubleshooting 2 - Checking Filter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way to check if your internal Filter is NOT working is to open your website and go to Real-Time Report in Google Analytics. If you don’t have much traffic on your website, you will notice the 1 person on your website that has suspiciously the same location as yours (this is how I found out…).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, there is a better way to check.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this, you need to install two extensions in Google Chrome -&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/tag-assistant-by-google/kejbdjndbnbjgmefkgdddjlbokphdefk?hl=en&quot;&gt;Google Tag Assistant&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/google-analytics-debugger/jnkmfdileelhofjcijamephohjechhna?hl=en&quot;&gt;Google Analytics debugger&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make sure you enabled them both. Google Analytics Debugger needs to be explicitly turned on by clicking on its icon. They will appear then in the top right-hand side on your Google Chrome address bar like so:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure style=&quot;width: 50%&quot; class=&quot;align-center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/images/posts/Google-Analytics-Debugger-Tag-Assistant-icons.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Google Analytics Debugger and Tag Assistant Icons in Chrome&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now open your website and record a flow with Google Tag Assistant. If you need more info, here’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://support.google.com/analytics/answer/6280771&quot;&gt;how&lt;/a&gt; from Google.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;notice--info text-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;far fa-sticky-note&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; For our purposes, you don’t need to go through the whole flow. Just check one-two pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you finished recording, click &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Show Full Report&lt;/code&gt;. Make sure to check both boxes - for &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Test View&lt;/code&gt; and for &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;All Web Site Data&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will be directed to a Google Tag Assistant Recordings webpage with two reports - one by Tag Assistant and another one by Google Analytics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will see Tag Assistant Report by default. Navigate to Google Analytics Report in the top left corner:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/Google-Analytics-in-Tag-Assistant-Recordings.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Google Analytics Report in Google Tag Assistant Recording&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now go to Change location in the left pane (see pic above). Choose &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Use a specific IP address&lt;/code&gt; and enter your IP address on the right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/Google-Analytics-Report-Tag-Assistant-Location-Filter.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Location Filter in Google Analytics Report in Google Tag Assistant Recording&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember that we configured the Views in Filter differentely - enabled it for &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;All Web Site Data&lt;/code&gt; and disabled for &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Test View&lt;/code&gt;? So here it comes in handy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your Filter was set up correctly, you will see no data was recorded for &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;All Web Site Data&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/Google-Analytics-Report-Tag-Assistant-all-website-data.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Filter check in Google Analytics Report in Google Tag Assistant Recording&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Test View&lt;/code&gt; recorded some information about the user:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/Google-Analytics-Report-Tag-Assistant-test-view.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Filter check in Google Analytics Report in Google Tag Assistant Recording&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have the same information for both Views, this means that your Filter was not configured correctly. Try going through the steps described above again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thumbs up below if you found this post helpful!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy blogging.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>vinay hegde</name></author><category term="Google Analytics" /><category term="Minimal Mistakes Jekyll" /><category term="Google Tag Assistant" /><summary type="html">How to set Internal IP filter in Google Analytics and check that it is actually working.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">UPDATE: Modeling COVID-19 in Silicon Valley after 4 weeks of shelter-in-place order</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/04/07/UPDATE-Modeling-Coronavirus-in-Silicon-Valley.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="UPDATE: Modeling COVID-19 in Silicon Valley after 4 weeks of shelter-in-place order" /><published>2020-04-07T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-04-07T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/04/07/UPDATE-Modeling-Coronavirus-in-Silicon-Valley</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/04/07/UPDATE-Modeling-Coronavirus-in-Silicon-Valley.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is an UPDATE of my article &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cross-validated.com/Modeling-Coronavirus-in-Silicon-Valley/&quot;&gt;“Modeling Coronavirus in Silicon Valley”&lt;/a&gt; from March 23, 2020.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/coronavirus-unsplash-1000.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Coronavirus Unsplash CDC&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photo by &lt;a style=&quot;background-color:black;color:white;text-decoration:none;padding:4px 6px;font-family:-apple-system, BlinkMacSystemFont, &amp;quot;San Francisco&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Helvetica Neue&amp;quot;, Helvetica, Ubuntu, Roboto, Noto, &amp;quot;Segoe UI&amp;quot;, Arial, sans-serif;font-size:12px;font-weight:bold;line-height:1.2;display:inline-block;border-radius:3px&quot; href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@cdc?utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_campaign=photographer-credit&amp;amp;utm_content=creditBadge&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; title=&quot;Download free do whatever you want high-resolution photos from CDC&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;display:inline-block;padding:2px 3px&quot;&gt;&lt;svg xmlns=&quot;http://www.w3.org/2000/svg&quot; style=&quot;height:12px;width:auto;position:relative;vertical-align:middle;top:-2px;fill:white&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 32 32&quot;&gt;&lt;title&gt;unsplash-logo&lt;/title&gt;&lt;path d=&quot;M10 9V0h12v9H10zm12 5h10v18H0V14h10v9h12v-9z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;display:inline-block;padding:2px 3px&quot;&gt;CDC&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; 
 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;April 7 is the day when people could have returned to normal life. It is the last day of the first shelter-in-place order in Santa Clara County before it was extended till May 3. So where do we stand now? Is the new deadline also ephemeral? Let’s look at data to answer these questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cross-validated.com/Modeling-Coronavirus-in-Silicon-Valley/&quot;&gt;previous article&lt;/a&gt; on COVID-19 in Silicon Valley, I assumed the exponential growth and created a simple model with 3 scenarios - when coronavirus cases double every 6, 7 or 8 days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two weeks later I can now say that the true cases stay within the modeling scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/coronavirus-in-Silicon-Valley-model-vs-true.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Coronavirus in Silicon Valley - Model vs True Cases&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source&lt;/strong&gt;: Own modeling based on data from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sccgov.org/sites/phd/DiseaseInformation/novel-coronavirus/Pages/dashboard.aspx&quot;&gt;County of Santa Clara Public Health Department&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the plot above, we can see that the spread rate in Santa Clara County accelerated in the last week of March (true cases closer to 6 days doubling rate model) and then slowed down starting in April (true cases closer to 7 days doubling rate model).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The slower spread rate indicates that social distancing works.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;So what to expect in May?&lt;/strong&gt;
Well, I think the worst time is still ahead of us. If nothing changes, the number of coronavirus cases in Santa Clara County could variate between 17,000 and 38,000 by May 3 or reach 10,000 in the best case (see model &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cross-validated.com/Modeling-Coronavirus-in-Silicon-Valley/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). With such numbers it is hard to imagine the return to normal life in four weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But even if I am wrong (and I hope so!), the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gxAaO2rsdIs&amp;amp;feature=youtu.be&quot;&gt;simulations done by a popular math blogger 3Blue1Brown&lt;/a&gt; show that not isolating all cases might lead to the second wave. So we need &lt;strong&gt;effective disease control - testing, quarantine &amp;amp; medical treatment - combined with social distancing&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until a vaccine against coronavirus is invented, we have to face the new reality and practice social distancing in earnest.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>vinay hegde</name></author><category term="COVID-19 in Bay Area" /><summary type="html">Shelter-in-place order seems to work - evidence shows a slow down in spread of Coronavirus in Silicon Valley.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My Experience with Insight Fellowship</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/04/06/Insight-Fellowship-Review.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My Experience with Insight Fellowship" /><published>2020-04-06T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-04-06T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/04/06/Insight-Fellowship-Review</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/04/06/Insight-Fellowship-Review.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/insight-data-science-1000.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Insight Data Science webpage&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      INSIGHT Data Science

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Somebody posted a question today on a forum about the &lt;a href=&quot;http://insightfellows.com&quot;&gt;Insight Fellowship&lt;/a&gt;. This prompted me to write about my experience with Insight Data Science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I applied to the INSIGHT Data Science in San Francisco three times in 2019, went through 5 interviews and still was rejected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some background about me - I have a PhD in Political Science from a non-US university and self-learned Data Science. I also started to code in Python around February 2019, so I was kind of fresh in my DS skills and was not yet ready for hard technical questions during the interview.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;target-audience&quot;&gt;Target Audience&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fellowship is not for somebody fresh out of college. The preference is given to those holding a PhD in STEM. Based on my own &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cross-validated.com/Insight-Data-Science-Fellows/&quot;&gt;analysis of the Insight Fellows&lt;/a&gt; published on the program’s website, almost half of the fellows hold PhD in (Astro)Physics or Neuroscience. Although I heard that they didn’t update  this information, so the data might be outdated. Still, it gives the idea about the typical profile of an Insight Fellow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-process&quot;&gt;Interview Process&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The interview process wasn’t particularly difficult - you get about 30 mins to introduce yourself and talk about your Data Science project, showcasing your code and communicating the results online via Zoom. The “hiring” manager then asks some technical questions based on your project to evaluate your knowledge of Statistics/ML algorithms - the usual stuff that you would expect during interview for Data Science positions. My impression is that you have to be experienced in Data Science before starting the Fellowship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fellowship&quot;&gt;Fellowship&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is also better if you have some project in mind during the interview, but is not necessary. This is because you will be working on your own project in a very short time frame during the fellowship. You learn by doing and through collaboration with others. So this is not a bootcamp where you get lectured.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talking to other Insight Fellows, I learned also that they facilitate interviews with companies they cooperate with. These partnerships are not stable and change for each cohort. I got an impression that these are mostly startups looking for qualified candidates for senior roles or roles with little supervision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;employment-prospects&quot;&gt;Employment Prospects&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Completing an Insight Fellowship doesn’t guarantee finding a job. This could have been true about 4-5 years ago, when the Data Science was just getting popular and there was not so much competition. I talked to two DS Insight Fellows who completed the fellowship in 2013 and 2017 - they found jobs in prestigious companies in Silicon Valley and Insight indeed made a difference for them. At the same time, I talked to a DS Insight Fellow who graduated recently and couldn’t secure a job even after completing the fellowship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, the interviews I had are very subjective and all have different stories, so I don’t want to generalize. My own impression is, however, that the field of Data Science got in general extremely competitive, as more and more people are drawn to it and get specialized university degrees. The golden age of the ‘self-taught’ Data Scientists are over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Summing up, if you are academic with PhD in STEM and has Data Science skills, you have good chances of becoming an Insight Fellow. Although finding a job is not guaranteed, you will get an access to an incredible network with interesting, like-minded and very intelligent people - something that you might profit from throughout your career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite numerous rejections, I still recommend applying for the Insight Fellowship. Not only I got a chance to practice communicating Data Science results during the interviews and discover my weaknesses. It also motivated me to do my own version of the INSIGHT sprint. In about four weeks, I completed the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/k-bosko/IPO_bubble&quot;&gt;“IPO Bubble”&lt;/a&gt; project, in which I scraped data from NASDAQ and YahooFinance and modeled the IPO success on its first day of trading. So for me the experience was definitely worth it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>vinay hegde</name></author><category term="Insight Data Science Fellowship" /><summary type="html">In this post, I sum up my experience with application for the Insight Data Science Fellowship.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22/assets/images/posts/insight-data-science-1000.jpg%22%7D" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/%7B%22teaser%22=%3E%22/assets/images/posts/insight-data-science-1000.jpg%22%7D" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Modeling COVID-19 in Silicon Valley</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/03/23/Modeling-Coronavirus-in-Silicon-Valley.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Modeling COVID-19 in Silicon Valley" /><published>2020-03-23T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-03-23T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/03/23/Modeling-Coronavirus-in-Silicon-Valley</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/03/23/Modeling-Coronavirus-in-Silicon-Valley.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/coronavirus-unsplash-1000.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Coronavirus Unsplash CDC&quot; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      

    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photo by &lt;a style=&quot;background-color:black;color:white;text-decoration:none;padding:4px 6px;font-family:-apple-system, BlinkMacSystemFont, &amp;quot;San Francisco&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Helvetica Neue&amp;quot;, Helvetica, Ubuntu, Roboto, Noto, &amp;quot;Segoe UI&amp;quot;, Arial, sans-serif;font-size:12px;font-weight:bold;line-height:1.2;display:inline-block;border-radius:3px&quot; href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@cdc?utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_campaign=photographer-credit&amp;amp;utm_content=creditBadge&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; title=&quot;Download free do whatever you want high-resolution photos from CDC&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;display:inline-block;padding:2px 3px&quot;&gt;&lt;svg xmlns=&quot;http://www.w3.org/2000/svg&quot; style=&quot;height:12px;width:auto;position:relative;vertical-align:middle;top:-2px;fill:white&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 32 32&quot;&gt;&lt;title&gt;unsplash-logo&lt;/title&gt;&lt;path d=&quot;M10 9V0h12v9H10zm12 5h10v18H0V14h10v9h12v-9z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;display:inline-block;padding:2px 3px&quot;&gt;CDC&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A simple model of coronavirus spread in Silicon Valley shows that practicing social distance might help in slowing the spread of coronavirus. But if the growth rate doesn’t change, then in May we will face a critical situation similar to Italy in March.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; 
 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On March 16, 2020 Santa Clara County - home to Silicon Valley and to almost 2 mln people - issued a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sfchronicle.com/bayarea/article/Bay-Area-to-shelter-in-place-What-you-need-15135087.php&quot;&gt;‘shelter-in-place’ order&lt;/a&gt; in attempt to slow the spread of Coronavirus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been collecting data on Coronavirus cases in Santa Clara County for a week now. We had 155 cases when the order was declared. This number doubled a week later - 302 cases on March 22.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;covid-19-cases-in-santa-clara-county&quot;&gt;COVID-19 Cases in Santa Clara County&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Time&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Total Confirmed  Cases&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Hospitalized&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Deaths&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;16-Mar&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;155&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;56&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;17-Mar&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;175&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;56&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;18-Mar&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;189&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;62&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;19-Mar&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;196&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;65&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;20-Mar&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;263&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;93&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;22-Mar&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;302&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;108&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source&lt;/strong&gt;: Own compilation based on data provided by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sccgov.org/sites/phd/DiseaseInformation/novel-coronavirus/Pages/home.aspx&quot;&gt;the County of Santa Clara Public Health Department&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assuming exponential growth, we can model the coronavirus spread as following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\[ y(t) = y_0 e^{kt} \]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where 
&lt;br /&gt;
\(y_0\) - the number of cases on March 16 &lt;br /&gt;
\(y\) - the number of cases after certain time period (\(t\)) in days &lt;br /&gt;
\(k\) - continuous growth rate&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on this, we can model 3 scenarios:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if COVID-19 cases double each week (as now)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if cases double faster - each 6 days&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if cases double slower - each 8 days&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are my results:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/coronavirus-in-Silicon-Valley.png&quot; alt=&quot;Model of Coronavirus in Silicon Valley&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In reality, the numbers above will be different. Still, they give us a feeling of how things might go. If nothing changes, we might expect that situation will be pretty bad around May in Silicon Valley.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, as with any exponential growth, even change of one day in spreading speed makes a big difference. So practicing social distance should help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stay healthy!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>vinay hegde</name></author><category term="COVID-19 in Bay Area" /><summary type="html">A simple model of coronavirus spread in Silicon Valley shows that things get really bad in May 2020.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to render math equations on your Minimal Mistakes</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/03/23/How-to-render-math-on-Minimal-Mistakes.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to render math equations on your Minimal Mistakes" /><published>2020-03-23T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-03-23T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/03/23/How-to-render-math-on-Minimal-Mistakes</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/03/23/How-to-render-math-on-Minimal-Mistakes.html">&lt;p&gt;You need &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mathjax.org&quot;&gt;MathJax&lt;/a&gt; if you want to render mathematical equations on your Minimal Mistakes website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I first learned about it from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pwills.com/posts/2017/12/20/website.html&quot;&gt;the blog post by Peter Willis&lt;/a&gt; (thanks, Peter!) However, I couldn’t enable MathJax even after following his instructions. So here’s what I did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1&quot;&gt;1.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Add this snippet at the end of the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;scripts.html&lt;/code&gt; which is in the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_includes&lt;/code&gt; folder:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-html highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mathjax.org/#gettingstarted&quot;&gt;MathJax documentation&lt;/a&gt; says that with this snippet you won’t need to change anything with each new version of MathJax.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2&quot;&gt;2.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enable MathJax in &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_config.yml&lt;/code&gt; by adding &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;mathjax: true&lt;/code&gt; to the page defaults&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-yml highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# Defaults&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;defaults&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;# _posts&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;scope&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;path&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;type&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;posts&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;values&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;layout&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;single&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;author_profile&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;no&quot;&gt;true&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;read_time&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;no&quot;&gt;true&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;comments&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;no&quot;&gt;true&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;share&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;no&quot;&gt;true&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;related&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;no&quot;&gt;true&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;mathjax&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;no&quot;&gt;true&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;notice--info text-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;far fa-sticky-note&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; If you are using Docker, don’t forget to rebuild your container after making changes to &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_config.yml&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;docker build -t minimal-mistakes .
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically that’s it. Try rendering \(y_0\) using &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;\\(&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;\\)&lt;/code&gt; delimeters for inline equations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;\\[&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;\\]&lt;/code&gt; to display equations like this one:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\[ f(a) = \frac{1}{2\pi i} \oint_\gamma \frac{f(z)}{z-a} dz \]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;notice--info text-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;far fa-sticky-note&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; If things don’t work, check if the MathJax script is added to the page using Developer tools.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>vinay hegde</name></author><category term="MathJax" /><category term="Minimal Mistakes Jekyll" /><summary type="html">Enabling MathJax on Minimal Mistakes Jekyll theme</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Setting up A/B Test with Google Optimize - Example</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/28/Setting-Up-AB-test-with-Google-Optimize.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Setting up A/B Test with Google Optimize - Example" /><published>2020-02-28T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-02-28T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/02/28/Setting-Up-AB-test-with-Google-Optimize</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/28/Setting-Up-AB-test-with-Google-Optimize.html">&lt;p&gt;In this post I describe #how I set up my first A/B test using Google Optimize.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you haven’t yet installed it on your Minimal Mistakes website, you can read the #howto &lt;a href=&quot;/How-to-install-Google-Optimize/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;stating-the-objective&quot;&gt;Stating the Objective&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A/B test is a randomized experiment to test two variants in order to decide which performs better. Variant A is usually the original (or ‘control’ using the statistical term), while Variant B is the new version you want to test (or ‘treatment’).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my case, I decided to change the titles of my #howto series and see if I can get more pageviews. Right now, they are in the form of part I, II, III and IV. The &lt;strong&gt;original hypothesis&lt;/strong&gt; was that if I call my posts in this temporal progression style and link them all together through cross-reference, people would check other parts and so I generate more traffic. However, such an approach is targeted at complete starters - people who want to build their website from scratch (like me). What I didn’t realize at that time is that people search on Google how to solve their specific problems, which is not necessarily equal to “whole package” of website building. Since my major traffic source is Organic Search according to Google Analytics, it makes sense to rename the titles so that they reflect the different users needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So my A/B test will do the following - &lt;strong&gt;change titles of four posts on my index page from&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Personal Website with Minimal Mistakes Jekyll Theme HOWTO - Part I&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Personal Website with Minimal Mistakes Jekyll Theme HOWTO - Part II&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Personal Website with Minimal Mistakes Jekyll Theme HOWTO - Part III&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Personal Website with Minimal Mistakes Jekyll Theme HOWTO - Part IV&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;to&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How to install Minimal Mistakes with Docker&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How to customize Minimal Mistakes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How to host personal website on GitHub Pages and use private domain&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How to improve SEO, enable comments and add Google Analytics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simpler and neater, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;setting-up-new-ab-test&quot;&gt;Setting up new A/B test&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Run Google Optimize in Chrome so that you can easily edit your webpage with Optimize Chrome extension later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Google Optimize go to your container and click on “Create experience”. Give it a name and choose what type of experiment you want to conduct.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since my goal is just to test two versions of title, I went with A/B test. If I wanted to test, say changing the title and changing the color of the link from blue to red as it appears on my website, I would need a Multivariate test for that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/Google-Optimize-create-experience.png&quot; alt=&quot;Google Optimize Create Experience&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we need to “Add variant”, give it a name and edit it with the help of Optimize Chrome extension. The process is rather straitforward - click on title -&amp;gt; Edit element from the bar on the right -&amp;gt; Edit text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new version of the index page I will be testing looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/Google-Optimize-Editing-Variant.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Google Optimize Editing a Variant&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we need to decide if we want to change weights. I decided not to do it and go with the custom 50/50 split, meaning that half of the users will be exposed to the original version of the page and another half will see a modified version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/Google-Optimize-weights.png&quot; alt=&quot;Google Optimize Targeting and Variants Set Up&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the next step, I linked my Google Analytics account for measurement and set up Custom objectives. Here’s the example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/Google-Optimize-Setting-up-Custom-Objective.png&quot; alt=&quot;Google Optimize Setting Up Custom Objectives&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I am allowed to add simultaneously only 3 objectives, I decided to go with the aggregated page views for all 4 pages and then add two more on the pages that were most viewed according to the Google Analytics report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/Google-Optimize-Objectives-1000.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Google Optimize Objectives Overview&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, now my experiment is ready to run!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will report the results in a separate post. Stay tuned! :)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>vinay hegde</name></author><category term="A/B Testing with Google Optimize" /><category term="Minimal Mistakes Jekyll" /><summary type="html">How to create A/B test with Google Optimize</summary></entry></feed>